Guide to the Trent history of medicine manuscripts collection, [1588?], 1661-1994 and undated, bulk 1750-1980
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Trent History of Medicine manuscript collection [1588?], 1661-1994 and undated, bulk 1750-1980, (780 collections; approximately 6,000 items)
  - Goodhue, Edward Solon, 1863-1935. Papers, 1900-1909 and undated, (11 items) (Box 5)
    Physician and specialist on leprosy. Mostly letters (ALS). W.D. Alexander writes on Hawaiian history and refers to Goodhue's book. Drs. Fontoynont, Miyajima, Jeanselme, Montizombert, Némorin and Anpeville write in reply to Goodhue's requests for information on literature on leprosy in their respective countries. Drs. Lie and Hansen of Bergen writes with reference to the Second International Leprosy Congress held in 1909. M.F. Obregon writes regarding an appointment. Among the letters is a typed manuscript, with answers to question on leprosy, signed by an unknown person.
  - Goodson, John. Document, 1691, Oct. 16, (1 item) (Box 5)
    First English physician to come to Pennsylvania under Penn's charter and commissioner of property (1686-1701). Holograph document, signed. Deed for a grant of land. On verso, a receipt for quit rent due on the granted, dated 1739, and a certificate of entry in the Office for Recording of Deeds, dated 1755.
  - Gosselin, Athanase-Léon, 1815-1887. Letter, 1854, June 9, (1 item) (Box 5)
    French surgeon. Letter (ALS). Informs recipient of his brother's promotion and thanks him for his efforts.
  - Goudareau, J. M. C. Letter, 1822, Aug. 19, (1 item) (Box 5)
    French physician and translator of the work of Johann Peter Frank. Letter (ALS). A personal letter.
  - Gould, Augustus Addison, 1805-1866. Papers, 1825-1851 and undated, (9 items) (Box 5)
    Physician and naturalist of Massachusetts. Letters (ALS). Gould writes of his life as tutor to the family of Mr. McBlair, a wealthy manufacturer of Jericho, Maryland, in long, detailed letters to his father, Nathaniel Duren Gould. In the earlier letters, he describes the trip from Boston, the roads and landscape, and presents a pencil drawing of the McBlair house and surrounding buildings. He writes of the day's routine, his teaching duties, and neighborhood news and gossip. He tells of how he listens for the mail wagon and of his disappointment with his pupils. His letters show that he did manage to keep up with events beyond Jericho, especially in the New England area. In his later letters, he professes a growing interest in medicine and botany. A much later letter informs William Jenks of his election as a Fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences.
  - Greely, Adolphus Washington, 1844-1935. Letter, 1886, May 5, (1 item) (Box 5)
    Arctic explorer. Letter (ALS). Hopes that provisions can be made for the survivors of his 1881-1883 Artic expedition.
  - Green, Samuel Abbott, 1830-1918. Letter, 1868, Feb. 18, (1 item) (Box 5)
    U.S. physician and historian. Letter (ALS). Requests information regarding places mentioned in a French diary, My campaigns in America: a journal kept by Count William de Deux-Ponts, 1780-1781, published by Green in 1868.
  - Grenfell, Wilfred Thomason, Sir, 1865-1940. Letter, 1914, Apr. 26, (1 item) (Box 5)
    English medical missionary. Letter (ALS). Enthusiastic reception of Lee's pamphlet on ventilation.
  - Griggs, Lee, 1790-1831. Papers, 1824-1831 and undated, (9 items) (Box 5)
    Physician in Jefferson County, Virginia (now West Virginia). Receipts of payment, miscellaneous notes, and a list of notes due to the estate of Dr. Lee Griggs, deceased.
  - Grisolle, Augustin, 1811-1869. Note, [Between 1830 and 1869], (1 item) (Box 5)
    French physician and clinician. Note (ANS). Arranges a meeting.
  - Guépin, Ange, 1805-1873. Letter, [Between 1825 and 1873], (1 item) (Box 5)
    French ophthalmologist. Letter (ALS). Writes of family matters.
  - Gull, William Withey, Sir, 1816-1890. Note, 1873, Jan., (1 item) (Box 5)
    British physician. Note (ANS). Asks the librarian of the Royal Society for the "Philosophical Transactions" of 1872.
  - Gulliver, George, 1804-1882. Papers, 1862-1868, (3 items) (Box 5)
    English anatomist and pathologist. Letters (ALS). In 1862 Gulliver writes on lectures, probably at the Royal College of Surgeons. In 1868 he writes to Robert Willis of the death of John Davy and inquires about a Dr. Tulk, translator of Robert Wagner's Elements of Physiology.
  - Gully, James Manby, 1808-1883. Letters, 1860, (2 items) (Box 5)
    English physician. Two letters (ALS). Introduces his son, asking for Potts' aid in establishing him as a solicitor. Recommends a water treatment for Mrs. Potts' back complaint.
  - Gunn, James Andrew, 1882-1958. Letter, 1930, Mar. 19, (1 item) (Box 5)
    English pharmacologist. Letter (ALS). Writes regarding the prospective sale of the 1785 edition of Withering's Account of the foxglove.
  - Guthrie, George James, 1785-1856. Letter, 1841, Nov. 26, (1 item) (Box 5)
    English surgeon. Letter (ALS). Asks addressee to consider Owen's report for publication in his Gazette.
  - Hackett, Cecil John. Papers, 1965-1971, (15 items) (Box 5)
    Letters (ALS). Hackett writes to Leonard J. Goldwater on mercury. Papers include carbon copies of Goldwater's typed letters, unsigned.
  - Hackett, C.W. Letter, 1875, Aug. 18, (1 item) (Box 5)
    Physician of Massachusetts. Letter (ALS). Hackett expresses his desire to visit the Polar regions and inquires if he may join an expedition.
  - Hahnemann, Samuel, 1755-1843. Letter, 1828, Aug. 25, (1 item) (Box 5)
    Founder of homeopathy. Letter (ALS). Writes of the fourth edition of his work, Organon der rationellen Heilkunde, and of its eventual translation into English.
  - Hale, Richard. Document, 1720, Sept. 29, (1 item) (Box 5)
    English physician. Document, signed. Authorizes the sale of his stock in the Company of Merchants of Great Britain Trading in the South Seas and other Parts of America.
  - Halford, Henry, Sir, bart., 1766-1844. Papers, 1819-1842 and undated, (8 items) (Box 5)
    Physician to the British royal family. Letters (ALS). Halford gives medical advice, writes a letter of recommendation, issues a bulletin on the condition of King George IV, discusses vaccination of the poor, and agrees to subscribe to some books. Holograph manuscript, in an unknown hand, provides biography.
  - Hall, James, 1811-1898. Letter, 1840, Apr. 18, (1 item) (Box 5)
    U.S. geologist and paleontologist. Letter (ALS). Reports the results of a meeting with the Governor regarding the addressee's drawings.
  - Hall, Larry G. Document, 1821, Apr. 23, (1 item) (Box 5)
    Physician of Ulster County, New York. Document, signed by Benj. R. Bevier, President of the Medical Society of Ulster County, attests that Larry G. Hall is a member of the Society and entitled to practice in the state.
  - Haller, Albrecht von, 1708-1777. Papers, 1763-1770 and undated, (3 items) (Box 5)
    Swiss scientist. Letters (ALS). Malcolm Flemyng writes, in English, to Haller on medical matters. He sends a second letter, in Latin, in which he refers to Haller's Physiology and to John Locke. Haller writes, in French, to Ignazio Somis, reporting on fever in the family, malaria in Germany and other matters.
  - Halliday, Andrew, Sir, 1781-1839. Letter, 1827, Aug. 7, (1 item) (Box 5)
    English military physician. Letter (ALS). Regarding postage.
  - Hammond, William Alexander, 1828-1900. Papers, 1862-1886, (11 items) (Box 5)
    U.S. physician and novelist. Letters (ALS). Writes regarding proofs and corrections of his novels. Recommends S. Weir Mitchell for a Jefferson Medical College professorship.
  - Hare, Robert, 1781-1858. Papers, 1825-1858, (5 items) (Box 5)
    Chemist of Philadelphia. Letters (ALS). Hare thanks a Dr. Muaran for the medical attention given to Robert Waln; discusses land investment with Edward S. Burd; writes to Zachariah Allen regarding the "cuts" used in his publications; and recommends Emile Therouanne of Paris to R. Gilmor. There is also an obituary notice.
  - Harel du Tancrel, Augustin, d. 1833. Letter, undated, (1 item) (Box 5)
    French physician and medical editor. Letter (ALS). Relating to publication matters.
  - Harley, John, 1833-1921. Papers, 1867-1869 and undated, (6 items) (Box 5)
    English physician and chemist. Letters (ALS) to Harley. S. W. Moore writes on the physiological chemistry of the brain. Sir Thomas Smith (1833-1909) of King's College, Edinburgh, writes on pharmacology.
  - Harrell, George T. Letter, 1996, June 7, (1 item) (Box 5)
    Physician, graduate of Duke University Medical Center, class of 1936. Letter (ALS). Accompanies a reprint of an article by Harrell, "Multiple hereditary telangiectases with recurring hemorrhage: a rare disease of clinical interest to Osler", and elaborates upon its contents.
  - Harris, George, 1722-1796. Letter, 1787, Apr. 25, (1 item) (Box 5)
    English philanthropist and benefactor of St. George's and Westminster Lying-in Hospitals. Letter (ALS). Writes to Clark (1739-1831), Chamberlain of London and president of Christ's Hospital, regarding Greek literature.
  - Harris, Thaddeus Mason, 1768-1842. Letter, 1797, Jan. 27, (1 item) (Box 5)
    Unitarian minister, naturalist and antiquarian. Letter (ALS). Sends copies of Bentley's lectures, promises more.
  - Harris, Thaddeus William, 1795-1856. Letter, 1835, Dec. 9, (1 item) (Box 6)
    Physician, botanist and entomologist of Cambridge, Mass. Letter (ALS). Asks Brown, a bookseller, to send volumes of the Boston Journal of Natural History to Mr. A. Halsey of Hartford, and to see that the journal is on sale and advertised in the principal cities and towns.
  - Harris, Thomas, 1784-1861. Papers, 1834-1848 and undated, (3 items) (Box 6)
    Physician and naval surgeon of Philadelphia. Letters (ALS). Writes to Commodore Jacob Jones regarding the naval asylum property and to W. P. C. Barton, from the Navy Department, regarding travel expenses.
  - Hart, Albert Bushnell, 1854-1943. Papers, 1912-1928, (2 items) (Box 6)
    U.S. historian. Letter (TLS). Hart answers John Thomas Lee's inquiries regarding Alexander Hamilton's Itinerarium. Also included is a letter from J. R. H. Moore to Lee, in which Moore describes his copy of the book, which he wishes to sell.
  - Hart, Ernest Abraham, 1835-1898. Papers, 1873-1895 and undated, (18 items) (Box 6)
    London physician and editor of the British Medical Journal. Note (ANS) to Hart, relating to social engagements and editorial matters, from Samuel Wilks, Alfred Baring Garrod, John Simon, George Burrows, Thomas Lauder Brunton, William Stokes, Thomas Spencer Wells, Henry Thompson, Joseph Fayrer, James Paget and John Russell Reynolds, among others. Oddly, one note is dated 4 Feb. 18.
  - Hartshorne, David. Deed, 1720, Aug. 5, (1 item) (Box 6)
    Physician of Norwich, Conn. Holograph document, signed. Records sale of eight acres to Israel Lothrup. Notarized by Richard Bushnell, Justice of the Peace.
  - Harvey, William, 1578-1657. Document, 1661, (1 item) (Box 6)
    Holograph document. A bill presented for "writings made and business done for Mr. Michael Harvey and Mr. William Harvey his brother".
  - Heberden, William, 1710-1801. Letter, 1776, July 11, (1 item) (Box 6)
    English physician and classical scholar. Letter (ALS). Writes of the death of Jeremiah Markland.
  - Helmholtz, Hermann von, 1821-1894. Note, undated, (1 item) (Box 6)
    German physiologist and physicist. Note (ANS).
  - Henry, Joseph, 1797-1878. Letters, 1833, 1856, (2 items) (Box 6)
    Thomas Cooper, president of South Carolina College, writes to Henry requesting the details on a new electromagnet that Henry has constructed. James Melville Gillin writes to Henry in 1856 about the shipment of two volumes of an unknown publication.
  - Henry, William, 1774-1836. Papers, 1806-1834, (3 items) (Box 6)
    English chemist and physician. Letters (ALS). William Hey writes Henry on calculi. Henry replies to Thomas Thompson's request for advice on how to dispose of the mineralogical collection of his brother-in-law, William Phillips. In this letter, Henry mentions geologist William Buckland. Invites Faraday on request of the Committee of the Manchester Royal Institution to give a course of lectures on chemistry. Informs him, however, that the Institution may not be able to supply all of the desired laboratory equipment.
  - Henslow, John Stevens, 1796-1861. Letter, 1840, July 15, (1 item) (Box 6)
    English botanist and geologist. Letter (ALS). Conveys his willingness to collaborate in the preparation of the Dictionary.
  - Herbert of Lea, Sidney, Baron, 1810-1861. Letter, 1858, Dec. 29, (1 item) (Box 6)
    British statesman. Letter (ALS). Writing to Reeve, Registrar to the Judiciary Committee of the Privy Council, describes the conditions of the infirmary at Winchester, complaining that inadequate ventilation produces 'hospital gangrene' in the patients.
  - Herr, Georges. Note, 1856, Sept. 25, (1 item) (Box 6)
    French physician and composer. Notes (ANS). A cordial note.
  - Hersey, Ezekiel, 1709-1770. Document, 1764, Mar. 8, (1 item) (Box 6)
    Physician of Massachusetts. Holograph document, signed. Payment received of Thomas Walley for twine.
  - Heurteloup, Nicolas, Baron, 1750-1812. Letter, 1801, Oct. 3, (1 item) (Box 6)
    French surgeon. Letter (ALS). Heurteloup, in his official capacity, replies to the inquiries of a Citizen Veneuere, a young surgeon at Bergerac, Department of Dordogne.
  - Hibbert, Samuel, 1782-1848. Letter, 1842, Sept. 2, (1 item) (Box 6)
    English geologist and antiquary. Letter (ALS). A personal letter relating the reasons for his third marriage. Hibbert also mentions mutual acquaintances, his travel plans, and a change of residence.
  - Hicks, H. Letter, 1804, May 12, (1 item) (Box 6)
    Letter (ALS). Discusses means of improving Dr. Jenner's financial situation and the possibility for a successful vaccination project in the East Indies.
  - Hincks, Thomas S. Hawkesford. Papers, 1873-1874, (7 items) (Box 6)
    Medical student at the University of Edinburgh. Certificates of attendance at lecture courses at the University of Edinburgh and class certificates of merit. Signed by Daniel Rutherford Haldane, practice of medicine; W. R. Sanders, pathology and anatomy; Thomas Laycock, clinical lectures on medicine; Thomas Grainger Stewart, practice of physic; Alexander R. Simpson, midwifery; James Spencer, surgery; and Robert Christison, materia medica.
  - Hitchcock, Edward, 1828-1911. Papers, 1852-1855, (2 items) (Box 6)
    Physician and faculty member, Amherst College. Letter (ALS) and holograph note, unsigned. In the letter Hitchcock arranges for the shipping and handling of a box of shells and other items.
  - Hodge, Hugh Lenox, 1796-1873. Letter, 1826, Dec. 21, (1 item) (Box 6)
    Obstetrician of Philadelphia. Letter (ALS) of recommendation for Andrew E. Kennedy.
  - Hodgkin, Thomas, 1798-1866. Papers, 1850 and undated, (2 items) (Box 6)
    English physician and historian. Letter (ALS) which briefly refers to the Aborigines Protection Society, which Hodgkin founded in 1838. A holograph note in an unknown hand gives biographical details.
  - Holland, Henry, Sir, 1788-1873. Letter, 1826, June 27, (1 item) (Box 6)
    English physician. Holograph letter, unsigned. Holland explains the circumstances which lead him to believe that his servant was mistakenly presented with a summons to service in the militia.
  - Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1809-1894. Papers, 1850-1885, (5 items) (Box 6)
    Physician, poet and essayist of Boston. Letters (ALS) on family genealogy; poems; and an ink cartoon drawing, on the reverse of one of the poems.
  - Holyoke, Edward Augustus, 1728-1829. Letter, 1792, Jan. 16, (1 item) (Box 6)
    Physician of Salem, Mass. Letter (ALS). Commends Wigglesworth's calculation of life expectancy figures from bills of mortality, collected by Holyoke, among others; confesses himself at a loss to explain why Americans enjoy a longer life expectancy than do the Swedish; and expresses his opinion that a tontine is a lottery and thus encourages gambling.
  - Home, Everard, Sir, 1756-1832. Document, 1803, June 1, (1 item) (Box 6)
    English surgeon. Autograph document, signed. Certifies that Lieutenant Colonel Grace returned from Minorca in ill health and thus incapable of military service.
  - Horner, Kate Z. Note, 1895, Sept. 18, (1 item) (Box 6)
    First woman elected coroner in the U.S. Note (ANS). Informs addressee that she was elected coroner the previous year.
  - Horner, William E. (William Edmonds), 1793-1853. Letter, 1839, Aug. 6, (1 item) (Box 6)
    Professor of anatomy and dean of the medical department of the University of Pennsylvania. Letter (ALS). Encloses writing samples of Caspar Wistar and Philip Syng Physick for Boyd's autograph collection.
  - Horsley, Victor, Sir, 1857-1916. Letter, 1886, Mar. 16, (1 item) (Box 6)
    English neurologist and neurosurgeon. Letter (ALS). Informs addressee that lectures he delivered in December will be published in the March or April issue of the British Medical Journal. Apparently, the lectures related to "the pathology of the spinal centres".
  - Horsley, William. Letter, 1823, Aug. 18, (1 item) (Box 6)
    English physician, brother of the Bishop Samuel Horsley (1733-1806). Letter (ALS). Informs Wright, surgeon aurist, of the case history of the bearer and refers him to his care.
  - Hosack, David, 1769-1835. Papers, 1801-1827, (2 items) (Box 6)
    Physician, botanist and mineralogist of New York. Document, signed, attests that he has declared all goods on entering the Port of New York; note (ANS) names someone to enter with the duty collector any parcels addressed to him from Europe.
  - Hough, John, Capt. Deed, 1735, Dec. 9, (1 item) (Box 6)
    Holograph, signed. Deed of land purchase. Witnessed by Benjamin Hide, Jr., and Daniel Lothrup.
  - Howe, Samuel Gridley, 1801-1876. Papers, 1851-1872 and undated, (4 items) (Box 6)
    Physician. The first to train the blind and deaf mutes in the United States. Letters (ALS) from Howe and a document, signed, in French from P. Flourens, acknowledging receipt of material sent to the Académie des Sciences.
  - Huchard, Henri, 1844-1911. Letter, 1894, Jan. 12, (1 item) (Box 6)
    French physician. Letter (ALS). Informs addressee of his wife's illness and instructs him to inform Dr. Variot that he will hold a promised clinic soon.
  - Hughes, Thomas. Papers, 1835-1846 and undated, (5 items) (Box 6)
    Chemist and druggist of Llandilo, Wales. His business was established in 1818. Documents, signed, relating to Thomas Hughes, his maternal grandmother, Joyce Morgan, his mother, Anne Hughes Samuel, her second husband, William Samuel, and the disposal of family property and goods. Includes a small bound manuscript notebook, undated, listing inventory with prices of stock in a general store: includes pharmaceutical items; a penciled note identified it as related to Hughes, Thomas. There is also a small print broadside advertising "Miscellaneous articles sold by Thomas Hughes, dispensing chemist."
  - Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859. Papers, 1816-1966 and undated, (26 items) (Box 6)
    German natural scientist and explorer. Letters (ALS), in French. Humboldt writes to P. H. Azaïs and Jules Berger de Xivrey on politics, philosophy, his expeditions, ethnology, natural history and the influence and inspiration of French thought. In 1966 Fritz Lange, of the Alexander-von-Humboldt-Kommission, writes to the Duke Medical Center Library regarding the Kommission's project to locate world-wide all correspondence to and from Humboldt.
  - Humphrey, Asahel. Papers, 1812-1835, (8 items) (Box 6)
    Physician of Salisbury. Holograph documents, signed. Receipts of payments made by the town of Salisbury to Dr. Asahel Humphrey, as well as Drs. M. A. Lee and William Walton.
  - Hunt, Harriot Kesia, 1805-1875. Letter, 1851, June 30, (1 item) (Box 6)
    U.S. physician, abolitionist, and suffragette. Discusses arrangements for an upcoming visit.
  - Hunter, John, 1728-1793. Letter, 1777, Sept. 7, (1 item) (Box 6)
    English physician. Letter (ALS). A cordial personal letter to Edward Jenner.
  - Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895. Letter, 1887, Sept. 30, (1 item) (Box 6)
    English zoologist and evolutionary biologist. Letter (ALS).
  - Hyde, William, Jr. Document, 1805, June 10, (1 item) (Box 6)
    Physician of Connecticut. Document, signed. Certificate to practice medicine, issued by the Connecticut State Medical Society to William Hyde Jr., signed by Jeremiah West, James Potter, Simon Wolcott, and Avery Downer.
  - Hyde, William, Jr. Papers, 1861 and undated, (16 items) (Box 6)
    Businessman, of Stonington, Connecticut; possibly same William Hyde, Jr. as above. Miscellaneous documents found in Hyde's daybooks, 1851-1861, which are part of the library's bound manuscript collection. Documents include foolscap bearing sums owed and names of clients. Of particular interest are three drafts of a petition, 1861, Conn., to the U.S. Senate and House of Representatives, that the Crittenden measures, introduced by Kentucky legislator John Jordan Crittenden, be adopted by all states in order to peacefully preserve the Union. Of related interest is a page bearing biblical passages regarding slaves.
  - Innes, James, 1754-1798. Letter, 1777, Jan. 28, (1 item) (Box 6)
    Lawyer and orator of Virginia. Letters (ALS). Gives an account of the death of General Mercer in the Battle of Princeton and of his burial in Philadelphia to Mrs. Gordon, a relative of the General.
  - Jackson, Charles Thomas, 1805-1880. Papers, 1871, (3 items) (Box 6)
    Physician and chemist. Letter (ALS) and two clippings. The first clipping puts forth W. T. G. Morton's claim to the discovery of the anesthetic properties of ether. In a letter to Joseph Hale Abbot, Jackson remarks bitterly on this public campaign, led by Drs. Bowditch and Bigelow. Jackson counters in the second clipping with his own claim to the discovery, as substantiated by several foreign juries.
  - Jackson, Hall, 1739-1797. Papers, 1775 and [before 1783], (2 items) (Box 6)
    Physician and army surgeon of New Hampshire. Two Letters (ALS). Jackson describes the political situation in New Hampshire in 1775 and voices his concern regarding an outbreak of smallpox in a small town on Lake Winnipesaukee, fearing that it might spread through the countryside.
  - Jackson, James, 1777-1867. Letter, undated, (1 item) (Box 6)
    Physician of Boston. Letter (ALS). Consents to Greenwood's preaching on the following day.
  - Jacobi, Mary Putnam, 1842-1906. Letter, undated, (1 item) (Box 6)
    Physician of New York. Letter (ALS). Informs addressee that she is obliged to decline both the topics and manner of correspondence suggested.
  - Jameson, Robert, 1774-1854. Letter, undated, (1 item) (Box 6)
    Scots physician and mineralogist. Letter (ALS). Regrets that his present state of health prevents him from visiting Anderson.
  - Jay, James, Sir, 1732-1815. Note, 1789, July 29, (1 item) (Box 6)
    Physician of New York, brother of Governor John Jay. Note (ANS). Order for half a hundred of whiting and a quarter of a hundred of yellow oker.
  - Jefferson, Geoffrey, Sir, 1886-1961. Letter, 1941, Nov. 19, (1 item) (Box 6)
    English surgeon. Letter (ALS). Expresses his desire to obtain a copy of a catalogue for his "Cushingiana." Muses upon the fact that people can think of books in the midst of war.
  - Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826. Note, 1820, Aug. 14, (1 item) (Box 6)
    Note with Jefferson's initials, sent from Monticello to a James Leitch (d. 1826), a Charlottesville merchant with whom Jefferson had extensive transactions, with a list of spices and quantities (allspice, nutmeg, ginger, cinnamon, mace), probably an order rather than a medical receipt as a modern note on the item mount suggests.